Nor should anything I say be taken as a justification of violations of human rights, like the mass death sentences handed out in Egypt earlier this week. But what I am saying is that we must challenge these Muslim fundamentalist movements because they threaten human rights across Muslim-majority contexts, and they do this in a range of ways, most obviously with the direct attacks on civilians by the armed groups that carry those out. But that violence is just the tip of the iceberg. These movements as a whole purvey discrimination against religious minorities and sexual minorities. They seek to curtail the freedom of religion of everyone who either practices in a different way or chooses not to practice. And most definingly, they lead an all-out war on the rights of women. Now, faced with these movements in recent years, Western discourse has most often offered two flawed responses. The first that one sometimes finds on the right suggests that most Muslims are fundamentalist or something about Islam is inherently fundamentalist, and this is just offensive and wrong, but unfortunately on the left one sometimes encounters a discourse that is too politically correct to acknowledge the problem of Muslim fundamentalism at all or, even worse, apologizes for it, and this is unacceptable as well. So what I'm seeking is a new way of talking about this all together, which is grounded in the lived experiences and the hope of the people on the front lines. I'm painfully aware that there has been an increase in discrimination against Muslims in recent years in countries like the U.K. and the U.S., and that too is a matter of grave concern, but I firmly believe that telling these counter-stereotypical stories of people of Muslim heritage who have confronted the fundamentalists and been their primary victims is also a great way of countering that discrimination. So now let me introduce you to four people whose stories I had the great honor of telling. Faizan Peerzada and the Rafi Peer Theatre workshop named for his father have for years promoted the performing arts in Pakistan. With the rise of jihadist violence, they began to receive threats to call off their events, which they refused to heed. And so a bomber struck their 2008 eighth world performing arts festival in Lahore, producing rain of glass that fell into the venue injuring nine people, and later that same night, the Peerzadas made a very difficult decision: they announced that their festival would continue as planned the next day. As Faizan said at the time, if we bow down to the Islamists, we'll just be sitting in a dark corner. But they didn't know what would happen. Would anyone come? In fact, thousands of people came out the next day to support the performing arts in Lahore, and this simultaneously thrilled and terrified Faizan, and he ran up to a woman who had come in with her two small children, and he said, "You do know there was a bomb here yesterday, and you do know there's a threat here today." And she said, "I know that, but I came to your festival with my mother when I was their age, and I still have those images in my mind. We have to be here." With stalwart audiences like this, the Peerzadas were able to conclude their festival on schedule. And then the next year, they lost all of their sponsors due to the security risk. So when I met them in 2010, they were in the middle of the first subsequent event that they were able to have in the same venue, and this was the ninth youth performing arts festival held in Lahore in a year when that city had already experienced 44 terror attacks. This was a time when the Pakistani Taliban had commenced their systematic targeting of girls' schools that would culminate in the attack on Malala Yousafzai. What did the Peerzadas do in that environment? They staged girls' school theater. So I had the privilege of watching "Naang Wal," which was a musical in the Punjabi language, and the girls of Lahore Grammar School played all the parts. They sang and danced, they played the mice and the water buffalo, and I held my breath, wondering, would we get to the end of this amazing show? And when we did, the whole audience collectively exhaled, and a few people actually wept, and then they filled the auditorium with the peaceful boom of their applause. And I remember thinking in that moment that the bombers made headlines here two years before but this night and these people are as important a story. Maria Bashir is the first and only woman chief prosecutor in Afghanistan. She's been in the post since 2008 and actually opened an office to investigate cases of violence against women, which she says is the most important area in her mandate. When I meet her in her office in Herat, she enters surrounded by four large men with four huge guns. In fact, she now has 23 bodyguards, because she has weathered bomb attacks that nearly killed her kids, and it took the leg off of one of her guards. Why does she continue? She says with a smile that that is the question that everyone asks— as she puts it, "Why you risk not living?" And it is simply that for her, a better future for all the Maria Bashirs to come is worth the risk, and she knows that if people like her do not take the risk, there will be no better future. Later on in our interview, Prosecutor Bashir tells me how worried she is about the possible outcome of government negotiations with the Taliban, the people who have been trying to kill her. "If we give them a place in the government," she asks, "Who will protect women's rights?" And she urges the international community not to forget its promise about women because now they want peace with Taliban. A few weeks after I leave Afghanistan, I see a headline on the Internet. An Afghan prosecutor has been assassinated. I google desperately, and thankfully that day I find out that Maria was not the victim, though sadly, another Afghan prosecutor was gunned down on his way to work. And when I hear headlines like that now, I think that as international troops leave Afghanistan this year and beyond, we must continue to care about what happens to people there, to all of the Maria Bashirs. Sometimes I still hear her voice in my head saying, with no bravado whatsoever, "The situation of the women of Afghanistan will be better someday. We should prepare the ground for this, even if we are killed." There are no words adequate to denounce the al Shabaab terrorists who attacked the Westgate Mall in Nairobi on the same day as a children's cooking competition in September of 2013. They killed 67, including poets and pregnant women. Far away in the American Midwest, I had the good fortune of meeting Somali-Americans who were working to counter the efforts of al Shabaab to recruit a small number of young people from their city of Minneapolis to take part in atrocities like Westgate. Abdirizak Bihi's studious 17-year-old nephew Burhan Hassan was recruited here in 2008, spirited to Somalia, and then killed when he tried to come home. Since that time, Mr. Bihi, who directs the no-budget Somali Education and Advocacy Center, has been vocally denouncing the recruitment and the failures of government and Somali-American institutions like the Abubakar As-Saddique Islamic Center where he believes his nephew was radicalized during a youth program. But he doesn't just criticize the mosque. He also takes on the government for its failure to do more to prevent poverty in his community. Given his own lack of financial resources, Mr. Bihi has had to be creative. To counter the efforts of al Shabaab to sway more disaffected youth, in the wake of the group's 2010 attack on World Cup viewers in Uganda, he organized a Ramadan basketball tournament in Minneapolis in response. Scores of Somali-American kids came out to embrace sport despite the fatwa against it. They played basketball as Burhan Hassan never would again. For his efforts, Mr. Bihi has been ostracized by the leadership of the Abubakar As-Saddique Islamic Center, with which he used to have good relations. He told me, "One day we saw the imam on TV calling us infidels and saying, 'These families are trying to destroy the mosque.'" This is at complete odds with how Abdirizak Bihi understands what he is trying to do by exposing al Shabaab recruitment, which is to save the religion I love from a small number of extremists. Now I want to tell one last story, that of a 22-year-old law student in Algeria named Amel Zenoune-Zouani who had the same dreams of a legal career that I did back in the '90s. She refused to give up her studies, despite the fact that the fundamentalists battling the Algerian state back then threatened all who continued their education. On January 26, 1997, Amel boarded the bus in Algiers where she was studying to go home and spend a Ramadan evening with her family, and would never finish law school. When the bus reached the outskirts of her hometown, it was stopped at a checkpoint manned by men from the Armed Islamic Group. Carrying her schoolbag, Amel was taken off the bus and killed in the street. The men who cut her throat then told everyone else, "If you go to university, the day will come when we will kill all of you just like this." Amel died at exactly 5:17 p.m., which we know because when she fell in the street, her watch broke. Her mother showed me the watch with the second hand still aimed optimistically upward towards a 5:18 that would never come. Shortly before her death, Amel had said to her mother of herself and her sisters, "Nothing will happen to us, Inshallah, God willing, but if something happens, you must know that we are dead for knowledge. You and father must keep your heads held high." The loss of such a young woman is unfathomable, and so as I did my research I found myself searching for Amel's hope again and her name even means "hope" in Arabic. I think I found it in two places. The first is in the strength of her family and all the other families to continue telling their stories and to go on with their lives despite the terrorism. In fact, Amel's sister Lamia overcame her grief, went to law school, and practices as a lawyer in Algiers today, something which is only possible because the armed fundamentalists were largely defeated in the country. And the second place I found Amel's hope was everywhere that women and men continue to defy the jihadis. We must support all of those in honor of Amel who continue this human rights struggle today, like the Network of Women Living Under Muslim Laws. It is not enough, as the victims rights advocate Cherifa Kheddar told me in Algiers, it is not enough just to battle terrorism. We must also challenge fundamentalism, because fundamentalism is the ideology that makes the bed of this terrorism. Why is it that people like her, like all of them are not more well known? Why is it that everyone knows who Osama bin Laden was and so few know of all of those standing up to the bin Ladens in their own contexts. We must change that, and so I ask you to please help share these stories through your networks. Look again at Amel Zenoune's watch, forever frozen, and now please look at your own watch and decide this is the moment that you commit to supporting people like Amel. We don't have the right to be silent about them because it is easier or because Western policy is flawed as well, because 5:17 is still coming to too many Amel Zenounes in places like northern Nigeria, where jihadis still kill students. The time to speak up in support of all of those who peacefully challenge fundamentalism and terrorism in their own communities is now. Thank you. (Applause)
Tampoco se debe tomar nada de lo que digo como justificación de la violaciones de los derechos humanos, como las sentencias de muerte masivas en Egipto a principios de esta semana. Lo que estoy diciendo es que debemos desafiar estos movimientos fundamentalistas musulmanes porque amenazan los derechos humanos en contextos de mayoría musulmana, y lo hacen de muchas formas diferentes. más evidentes por los grupos armados que llevan a cabo los ataques directos contra civiles. Pero esa forma de violencia es solo la punta del iceberg. Estos movimientos, como toda forma de discriminación contra las minorías religiosas y las minorías sexuales, tratan de restringir la libertad religiosa de cualquiera que practique de una manera diferente u opte por no practicar. Y más claramente, lideran una guerra total contra los derechos de las mujeres. Ahora, frente a estos movimientos en los últimos años, el discurso de Occidente ha ofrecido frecuentemente dos respuestas erróneas. La primera que uno encuentra a veces a la derecha, sugiere que la mayoría de los musulmanes son fundamentalistas, o que algo en el Islam es inherentemente fundamentalista. Esto es ofensivo y falso. Pero, por desgracia, en la izquierda uno a veces encuentra un discurso políticamente correcto pero que no conoce el problema del fundamentalismo musulmán en absoluto o, peor aún, que lo disculpa. Y esto es igualmente inaceptable. Así que lo que estoy buscando es una nueva forma de hablar de todo esto, que esté basada en las experiencias vividas y las esperanzas de la gente en los frentes de batalla. Estoy dolorosamente consciente de que existe un aumento de la discriminación contra los musulmanes en los últimos años, en países como el Reino Unido y los EE. UU., lo que también es un motivo de gran preocupación. Pero creo firmemente que contar estas historias de lucha contra el estereotipo de las personas de origen musulmán que han enfrentado a los fundamentalistas y han sido sus principales víctimas, es también una gran manera de contrarrestar esa discriminación. Así que ahora permítanme presentarles a cuatro personas cuyas historias tuve el gran honor de relatar. Faizan Peerzada y el taller teatral Rafi Peer, llamado así por su padre, ha promovido durante años las artes escénicas en Pakistán. Con el auge de la violencia yihadista, comenzaron a recibir amenazas de cancelar sus eventos, a las que negaron prestar atención. Y entonces un bombardero atacó su octavo Festival de Artes Escénicas en Lahore en 2008, produciendo una lluvia de vidrios que cayeron en el lugar e hirieron a 9 personas. Más tarde, esa misma noche, los Peerzadas tomaron una decisión muy difícil: anunciaron que su festival continuaría como estaba previsto para el día siguiente. Como dijo Faizan en el momento, si nos inclinamos ante los islamistas, quedaremos relegados a un rincón oscuro. Pero ellos no sabían lo que iba a suceder. ¿Vendría alguien? De hecho, miles de personas salieron el día siguiente para apoyar las artes escénicas en Lahore. Y esto emocionó y a la vez aterrorizó a Faizan, quien corrió hacia una mujer que había entrado con sus dos hijos pequeños, y le dijo: "¿Ud. sabe que hubo una bomba aquí ayer, y sabe que hay una amenaza para hoy aquí?". Y ella dijo: "Lo sé, pero yo vine a su festival con mi madre cuando yo tenía la edad de ellos, y todavía tengo esas imágenes en mi mente. Tenemos que estar aquí". Con audiencias incondicionales de este tipo, los Peerzadas fueron capaces de concluir su festival en la fecha prevista. Y entonces el siguiente año, perdieron todos sus patrocinadores debido al riesgo de seguridad. Cuando me reuní con ellos en 2010, estaban en medio del primer evento posterior que pudieron ofrecer en el mismo lugar. Ese fue el noveno Festival juvenil de artes escénicas celebrado en Lahore en un año en que esa ciudad ya había experimentado 44 ataques terroristas. Fue cuando los talibanes paquistanís habían comenzado su persecución sistemática de las escuelas de niñas que culminaría con el ataque a Malala Yousafzai. ¿Qué hacían los Peerzadas en ese momento? Organizaban teatro escolar para niñas. Tuve el privilegio de ver "Naang Wal", un musical en idioma punjabi, en que las niñas de la escuela secundaria de Lahore representaban todos los papeles. Cantaron y bailaron, actuaron de ratones y de búfalos de agua, y yo contenía la respiración, preguntándome, si podríamos llegar al final de este increíble espectáculo. Y al llegar al final, todo el público exhaló colectivamente, y unas pocas personas en realidad lloraron, y luego llenaron el auditorio con el estruendo pacífico de sus aplausos. Y recuerdo que pensé en ese momento que los atacantes habían sido noticia aquí dos años antes. Pero esa noche y esa gente son historias igualmente importantes. Maria Bashir es la primera y única fiscal general mujer en Afganistán. Ella ha estado en el cargo desde 2008 y de hecho abrió una oficina para investigar los casos de violencia contra las mujeres, que según ella es el área más importante en su mandato. Cuando me encontré con ella en su oficina en Herat, entró rodeada de 4 hombres grandes con enormes armas. De hecho, ahora tiene 23 guardaespaldas, porque ha capeado ataques con bombas que casi matan a sus hijos, y amputaron la pierna de uno de sus guardias. ¿Por qué sigue? Ella dice con una sonrisa, que esa es la cuestión que todo el mundo le pregunta. Como ella dice, "¿Por qué te arriesgas a no vivir?" Y es simplemente que para ella, un futuro mejor para todas las María Bashirs por venir, vale la pena el riesgo. Ella sabe bien que si la gente como ella no corre riesgos, no habrá un futuro mejor. Más adelante en la entrevista, la fiscal Bashir me dice lo preocupada que está por el posible resultado de las negociaciones del gobierno con los talibanes, las personas que han estado tratando de matarla. "Si les damos un lugar en el gobierno" pregunta, "¿quién protegerá los derechos de las mujeres?" Y ella insta a la comunidad internacional a no olvidar su promesa sobre las mujeres porque ahora quieren la paz con los talibanes. Unas pocas semanas después de que dejé Afganistán, vi un titular en Internet. Un fiscal afgano había sido asesinado. Consulté en Google desesperadamente, y por suerte me enteré ese día de que María no había sido la víctima, cuando por desgracia, otro fiscal afgano fue asesinado a tiros cuando se dirigía a trabajar. Y cuando oigo titulares como este ahora, creo que, a medida que las tropas internacionales salgan de Afganistán este año y los siguientes, tendremos que seguir cuidando lo que les sucede a las personas de allí, a todas las Maria Bashirs. A veces todavía oigo su voz en mi cabeza diciendo, sin bravuconadas de ningún tipo, "La situación de las mujeres en Afganistán será mejor algún día. Debemos preparar el terreno para esto, incluso si nos matan". No hay palabras adecuadas para denunciar a los terroristas de Al Shabaab que atacaron el Westgate Mall en Nairobi el mismo día de un concurso de cocina para niños en septiembre de 2013. Mataron a 67, incluyendo poetas y mujeres embarazadas. Allá lejos, en el medio oeste estadounidense, tuve la fortuna de conocer somalíes-estadounidenses que trabajaban en contrarrestar los esfuerzos de Al Shabaab, de reclutar a un pequeño número de jóvenes en su ciudad, en Minneapolis, para participar en atrocidades como Westgate. El estudiante Abdirizak Bihi sobrino Burhan Hassan de 17 años de edad, fue reclutado aquí en 2008, comprometido con Somalia y luego fue asesinado tratando de volver a casa. Desde ese momento, el Sr. Bihi, que dirige el Centro para la educación y la defensa somalí, sin ingresos, ha venido denunciando el reclutamiento y los fracasos del gobierno y las instituciones somalíes-estadounidenses como el Centro Islámico Abubakar As-Saddique, donde él cree que su sobrino se radicalizó durante un programa juvenil. Pero no se limita a criticar a la mezquita. También acusa al gobierno por su incapacidad de hacer más para evitar la pobreza en su comunidad. Dada su falta de recursos financieros, el Sr. Bihi ha tenido que ser creativo. Para contrarrestar los esfuerzos de Al Shabaab, para influir en los jóvenes más resentidos, a raíz de los ataques del grupo en 2010 a los espectadores de la Copa Mundial en Uganda, organizó un torneo de baloncesto en Ramadán en Minneapolis, como respuesta. Decenas de niños somalíes-estadounidenses salieron a abrazar el deporte a pesar de la fatua contra ellos. Jugaron baloncesto como Burhan Hassan nunca lo haría de nuevo. Por sus esfuerzos, el Sr. Bihi ha sido condenado al ostracismo por la dirección del Centro Islámico Abubakar As-Saddique, con el que solía tener buenas relaciones. Él me dijo: "Un día vimos al imán en la televisión llamándonos infieles y diciendo: "Estas familias están tratando de destruir la mezquita". Esto está en contradicción completa con la forma como Abdirizak Bihi entiende lo que él está tratando de hacer mediante la denuncia al reclutamiento de al Shabaab, para salvar la religión que yo adoro, de un pequeño número de extremistas. Ahora quiero contarles una última historia. La de una estudiante de derecho de 22 años de edad en Argelia, llamada Amel Zenoune-Zouani que tenía los mismos sueños de una carrera legal, como yo tuve en los años 90. Ella se negó a renunciar a sus estudios, a pesar de que los fundamentalistas luchaban contra el Estado argelino en ese entonces, amenazando a todos los que continuaran su educación. El 26 de enero de 1997, Amel subió al autobús en Argel, donde estudiaba para ir a casa y pasar la noche del Ramadán con su familia. Nunca llegaría a terminar sus estudios de derecho. Cuando el autobús llegó a las afueras de su ciudad natal, fue detenido en un puesto de control por los hombres del Grupo Islámico Armado. Portando su mochila, Amel fue bajada del bus y asesinada en la calle. Los hombres le cortaron el cuello y luego le dijeron a todo el mundo, "Si van a la universidad, el día llegará en que vamos a matarlas a todas, igual que a ella". Amel murió exactamente a las 5:17, lo sabemos, porque cuando cayó en la calle, su reloj se rompió. Su madre me mostró el reloj con la manecilla aún dirigida con optimismo hacia arriba hacia un 5:18 que nunca llegaría. Poco antes de su muerte, Amel había dicho a su madre, y a sus hermanas, "Nada nos va a pasar a nosotras, Inshallah, si Dios quiere. Pero si algo sucede, deben saber que morimos por aprender. Tú y papá deben mantener su cabeza bien alta". La pérdida de una mujer tan joven es insondable. Y al hacer mi investigación me encontré a mí misma en busca de la esperanza de Amel de nuevo. Su nombre incluso significa "esperanza" en árabe. Creo que la he encontrado en dos lugares. El primero es en la fuerza de su familia y todas las otras familias que siguen contando sus historias y que siguen con sus vidas a pesar del terrorismo. De hecho, la hermana de Amel, Lamia, se sobrepuso a su dolor, fue a la escuela de leyes, y practica como abogada hoy en Argel, algo que solo es posible porque los fundamentalistas armados fueron derrotados en gran parte del país. Y el segundo lugar en el que encuentro la esperanza de Amel está en todas partes en que las mujeres y los hombres continúan desafiando a los yihadistas. Debemos apoyar a todos aquellos que en honor de Amel continúan esta lucha por los derechos humanos en la actualidad, como la "Red de mujeres bajo leyes musulmanas". No es suficiente, ya que el defensor de los derechos de las víctimas, Cherifa Kheddar, me dijo en Argel, que no basta con combatir el terrorismo. También debemos cuestionar el fundamentalismo, porque el fundamentalismo es la ideología que sirve de soporte a este terrorismo. ¿Por qué será que la gente como ella, al igual que todos los demás, no son más conocidos? ¿Por qué será que todo el mundo sabe quién era Osama bin Laden y tan pocos conocen a todos los que enfrentan a los bin Laden en su propio ambiente? Tenemos que cambiar eso, por lo que les pido que por favor ayuden a compartir estas historias a través de sus redes. Miren de nuevo el reloj de Amel Zenoune, congelado para siempre. Y ahora por favor miren su propio reloj y decidan que este es el momento en que uds. se comprometen a apoyar a personas como Amel. No tenemos derecho de guardar silencio sobre ellos, porque es más fácil, o porque la política occidental es también deficiente. Porque las 5:17 aún están por venir a demasiadas Amel Zenounes en lugares como el norte de Nigeria, donde los yihadistas siguen matando estudiantes. El tiempo de hablar en apoyo de todos aquellos que pacíficamente desafían el fundamentalismo y el terrorismo en sus propias comunidades, es ahora. Gracias. (Aplausos)